Roland S. Morris Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Roland S. Morris Papers 1910-1943
MSS33613
Morris, Roland S. (Roland Sletor), 1874-1945
5,000 items
15 containers
6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Lawyer, diplomat, and educator. Correspondence, memoranda, speeches, reports, newspaper clippings, photographs, and other papers relating primarily to Morris's service as U.S. ambassador to Japan and to his special missions to Siberia.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bryan, William Jennings, 1860-1925--Correspondence.; Lansing, Robert, 1864-1928--Correspondence.; Long, Breckinridge, 1881-1958--Correspondence.; McCormick, Vance Criswell, 1872-1946--Correspondence.; Morris, Roland S. (Roland Sletor), 1874-1945.; Rowe, L. S. (Leo Stanton), 1871-1946--Correspondence.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924--Correspondence.
Organizations
University of Pennsylvania.
Subjects
Diplomatic and consular service, American--Japan.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Soviet Union.; International law.; Universities and colleges--Pennsylvania.
Places
Japan--Foreign relations--United States.; Siberia (Russia)--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union--Foreign relations--United States.; Soviet Union--History--Allied intervention, 1918-1920.; United States--Foreign relations--Japan.; United States--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.
Occupations
Diplomats.; Educators.; Lawyers.
Provenance
The papers of Roland S. Morris, lawyer, diplomat, and educator, were given to the Library of Congress by his children, Edward Shippen Morris and Sarah Morris Machold, in 1950.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Roland S. Morris are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1874 Born, Olympia, Wash.
1892 Graduated high school, Lawrenceville, N. J.
1896 A.B., Princeton University, Princeton, N.Y.
1899 L.L.B., University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pa. Began practice of law, Philadelphia, Pa.
1904 Member, firm of Duane, Morris and Heckscher
1908 1916 Chairman, Democratic Finance Committee of Pennsylvania
1913 1916 State chairman, Democratic Party in Pennsylvania
1917 1921 Ambassador extraordinary and plenipotentiary to Japan
1918 1919 Special mission to Siberia
1920 1921 Acting assistant secretary of state
1924 Professor of international law, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pa.
1928 1933 Pennsylvania State Board of Law Examiners
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Roland Sletor Morris (1874-1945) span the years 1910-1943. The collection contains correspondence, telegrams, memoranda, intelligence reports, speeches, newspaper clippings, photographs, and other papers relating primarily to Morris's service as ambassador to Japan (1917-1921) and to his special missions to Siberia (1918-1919). Included are typewritten copies of a translation of a diary of a Japanese mission to the United States (1860) and official telegrams exchanged with Secretary of State Robert Lansing, as well as material pertaining to the Allied intervenion in Siberia, 1918-1920. Also in the collection are papers pertaining to Morris's work as a professor of international law at the University of Pennsylvania. Correspondents include William Jennings Bryan, Robert Lansing, Breckinridge Long, Vance McCormick, Leo S. Rowe, and Woodrow Wilson.
Arrangement of the Papers
The papers are organized by type of material.
Container List
- General correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1910, June-1919, Apr. (Box 1)
  - 1919, May-1920, Jan., including a weekly report of Siberian Commission of the American Red Cross (Box 2)
  - 1920, Feb.-1938, Feb., undated (Box 3)
- Official telegrams (Box 4)
  - Secretary of state to United States Embassy, Tokyo, Japan (Box 4)
    - 1918, June 16-1919, Dec. (Box 4)
    - 1920, Jan.-1920, Apr. 30 (Box 5)
  - Exchanges by Morris and Robert Lansing regarding shipping, 1918, Feb.1-May 13 (Box 5)
  - Mainly from Morris to secretary of state, Washington, D.C. (Box 5)
    - 1918, May 2-Sept. 23 (Box 5)
    - 1919, July 10-1920, Apr. 27 (Box 5)
- Data on Japan (Box 6)
  - Reports, memoranda, diplomatic lists, printed matter, etc., including typescript copies of a translation of a diary of a Japanese mission to the United States (1860), with translator’s preface. (Box 6)
- Data on Siberia (Box 7)
  - Letters from commercial and banking firms; letters from Red Cross and YMCA; report on Proceedings of the Second Congress, Third Communist Internationale, Petrograd-Moscow, Russia, July-Aug. 1920 (from Pravda and Isvestia ); material regarding Stevens Railway Commission; etc. (Box 7)
  - Reports mainly from Asiatic Squadron of United States Fleet and from American Expeditionary Forces in Siberia, to Morris (Box 8)
  - Reports and memoranda regarding friction between forces of the United States and Japan in Siberia; atrocity photographs; etc. (Box 9)
- University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pa. (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1926-1943 (Box 10)
  - “University of Pennsylvania General,” correspondence, 1926-1928 (Box 10)
  - “University Museum,” letters received, 1937-1940 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous working papers, senior research papers, etc. (Box 11)
- Speeches by Morris (Box 12)
  - 1917-1924 (Box 12)
  - 1925-1939 (Box 13)
  - Undated (Box 14)
- Miscellany, mainly manuscript notes, clippings, and printed matter (Box 15)